Okay, today's דף daf is ס״ח. Samech-Chet. Okay, we pick up with
the משנה mishna at the bottom of ס״ז Samech-Zayin עמוד ב׳. Amud
Bet. We are continuing now with the עבודה. avoda. So we have
talked about sending the goat out, about about about the person who
actually would bring it to the edge, push it over,
and the fact that the תורה Torah says the בגדים bgadim become
טמא. tamei. The גמרא Gemara says, the משנה mishna says: When is
that? So one opinion is when it gets thrown over, but the
majority opinion is when it gets to the מדבר. midbar. המשלח את
השעיר, HaMeshaleach es HaSe'ir,
so when it leaves ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
And you know, that's also as we discussed a concept about three
questions: when did he עבד, avad,
what's the minimum needed in order to be יוצא yotzei the עבודה?
avoda? There it may be even drops dead after the וידוי. vidui.
Number two, when is it considered יצא מצותה, yatza mitzvata, you fulfilled
the מצוה? mitzvah? That may be as soon as it leaves ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. And then the third question is when actually, you know, the
completion of it pushing it off the cliff? At what stage did
the string become red within that? That also seems to possibly be
dependent whether it became red when it got to the מדבר, midbar,
did it get red when it went over the cliff? So how
the כפרה, kappara, how the sense of the full atonement corresponds to
the doing of the מצוה. mitzvah. This is something that we will
revisit today. Let's take a look now at the next משנה mishna
on the bottom of ס״ז Samech-Zayin עמוד ב׳. Amud Bet. בא לו
אצל פר ושעיר הנשרפין. Ba lo etzel par v'se'ir hanisrafin. So he
said, now we're back to the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. We had
been talking about this איש עתי, ish iti, but we're back to
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. He sent this goat to go with
this man who's now taking it over the cliff. He now turns
his attention to the goat and the and the ox, the one
he did the whole ritual of blood. Remember that's what he just
finished, just to remind us all. The first ritual he did, well
first he שחט shachat the ox, but then he did the whole
thing about the קטורת, ketoret, then he did the blood of the
ox, then he did the blood of the goat, you know, and
then he did it not only in the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh HaKodashim,
on the פרוכת, parochet, אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, מזבח. mizbeach. He poured
it at the base of the outer מזבח, mizbeach, sent off the
goat, and now he had drawn the lots earlier on, drawn the
lots at the time of the getting ready for the קטורת ketoret
and so on. And now, sent off the goat, now he is
coming to finish up with the carcasses of the ox and the
goat. So he came to the ox and the goat that are
burnt because that's what you're gonna do with their carcasses. קרען והוציא
את אימוריהם. Kera'an v'hotzi es imureihem. He tore them open, you know,
so he he split them open in order to take out, as
we'll see, their innards. הוציא את אימוריהם, hotzi es imureihem, he took
out their fats and their their inner organs because this is going
to be burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach. The blood was not on
the outer מזבח, mizbeach, it was on the inner area, but like
all קרבנות, korbanot, the fats and
the inner organs are burnt on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. One minute,
נתנם במגיס, netanam b'magis, he put them in a vessel, some type
of of a bowl. והקטירן על גבי המזבח, V'hiktiran al gabei ha'mizbeach,
he burnt them on the מזבח. mizbeach. קלען במקלעות, Kela'an b'miklaot,
he sort of twisted them, braided them is what רש״י Rashi says,
on top of some type of a wooden frame, a carrying frame.
והוציאן לבית השריפה, V'hotzi'an l'veis hasreifa, and not he, but they, literally
it says he took them out but somebody else took them out
to the place that they'd be burnt because, you know, things that
the blood is put on the inner and on the in the
היכל, Heichal, in the inner inside, not on the outer מזבח mizbeach
but on the inside, the תורה Torah says that you take their
carcasses and you burn them outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
It says it specifically here, it says it in general by other
animals like פר העלם דבר par helam davar that we've mentioned before
that the blood is brought on the inside, you burn their bodies
on the outside. So that's what he did. He sent them to
be burnt, he didn't do it personally. ומאימתי מטמאין בגדים? U'mei'emasi mitam'in
bgadim?
So same type of question we asked by when the guy who
takes the goat out and runs it off the cliff, when his
בגדים bgadim become טמא. tamei. Because the תורה Torah says that he
and his clothes become טמא, tamei, not just the בגדים, bgadim, he
and his clothes become טמא. tamei. So here too it says that
the והשורף אותם יכבס בגדיו, v'hasoref osam yechabes bgadav, the one who
burns them, his clothes become טמא, tamei, he and his clothes. So
when does that happen? משיצאו חוץ לחומת עזרה, Misheyatze'u chutz l'chomas azara,
very similar to what we said by the goat. By the goat
we said חוץ לחומת ירושלים chutz l'chomas Yerushalayim though, I'll mention. There
we said when it leaves ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Here we say as soon
as it leaves the עזרה. azara. Although the תורה Torah says והשורף
אותם, v'hasoref osam, no, you are going out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We'll
find out, we'll find out about that. Yeah, it's not clear where
it would be brought out, but we'll find out in the גמרא.
Gemara. Was it brought out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? So so again by
the case by the goat, maybe for us it was a חידוש
chiddush that it would be before it would go over the cliff.
But the פסוקים psukim don't talk about the cliff. The פסוקים psukim
just say והמשלח את השעיר לעזאזל, v'hameshaleach es hase'ir l'Azazel, the guy
who's sending it out. So there we say even without going over
the cliff, even just going outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Here the פסוקים
psukim say the one who burns it becomes טמא tamei and his
clothes become טמא, tamei, but the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying
even without burning it, just leaving the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash you
become טמא. tamei. רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer. רבי שמעון אומר
משתצת האור ברובן, Rabbi Shimon Omer Mishetetzat Ha'or Beruban,
again a more literal approach, or the more of the final step,
only once the fire has seized the majority of the carcass, only
then are you טמא. Tamei. So more, now I will remind you
also that it is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon of the previous משנה
Mishna that says by the goat that the person only becomes טמא
Tamei when the goat goes over the cliff. So there's a definite
parallel that the תנא קמא Tanna Kama says when it leaves the
relevant environment, when it's on the way, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says only when it's done, when it goes over the cliff or
when the carcasses are being burnt. Even though according to the תנא
קמא Tanna Kama again there's a difference, by the goat it's המשלח
את העזאזל המדברה, Hamishalayach Et HaAzazel Hamidbarah, so it has to leave
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, this according to him just when it leaves the עזרה
Azarah already the person who's involved in it becomes טמא. Tamei. Yes
Michael?
So I just find it interesting that he has to do the
ripping out of the אימורין. Imurin. Do we tell him he's doing
that with the תמיד Tamid and he's doing that with the other
מוספין? Musafim?
Yeah so it's a good question. It's a good question whether he
literally does it. It does say בא לו, Ba lo, so it
sounds like he himself is doing it now. He is going to
burn the אימורין, Imurin, okay, but right is he himself the one
getting his hands all bloody here? He's wearing these white gorgeous בגדי
כהונה. Bigdei Kehuna. He's the one. He's the one gonna be cutting
them open. I mean look the the what's it called, the not
the predicate, but anyway the subject of the verb is ambiguous because
when it gets to the next part it says הוציאן לבית השריפה,
Hotzi'an Leveit HaSreifa,
literally it means and he takes them out, right, והוא הוציא אותם
לבית השריפה, Vehu Hotzi Otam Leveit HaSreifa, but it's not him. So
exactly whether he is the one actually cutting them open, I don't
know.
So the question is if he is, why would it be by
this as opposed?
Yeah it's a very good question, right, it would not make any
sense why he should be the one doing it. He does not
require to be done by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the actual
you know cutting open of them. The burning of the אימורין, Imurin,
you know, is a different question but right. I think that's a
you know that's a very good question and again I don't know
I would have to see if there's a discussion whether it literally
means him. Okay so let's take a look now at the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says והקטירן סלקא דעתך. Vehiktiran Salka Da'atach.
It says he puts their innards in a vessel and he burns
them up on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So the גמרא Gemara says literally
you really think he's burning them up? Now it doesn't mean him
as opposed to somebody else. It means this isn't the time yet
to burn them up. The burning of the innards happens way at
the end, happens after the other עבודות, Avodot, after the מוסף, Musaf,
after you take out the כף. Kaf. It doesn't happen now. It
happens later. So what does it mean he puts them in the
vessel and burns them? He doesn't offer them yet.
Wait why doesn't he offer them now?
Says the גמרא Gemara it's not that he can't but like we
know from the סדר עבודה Seder Avodah that he doesn't. Okay? What?
I don't know but we'll see later in the משניות Mishnayot that
this is not what happens at this time in the סדר עבודה.
Seder Avodah. Okay so what do you mean that he's doing it
now? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
אימא להקטירן על גבי מזבח. Ella Eima Lehaktiran Al Gabei Mizbe'ach. Don't
say that he does it he now offers them up, it says
he puts them in for the purpose of later burning them on
the מזבח Mizbe'ach but it doesn't literally mean that right now is
the moment he burns them on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. We'll find out
later that that happens at a later time. Now there's a large
תוספות Tosafot here and there's a רש"י Rashi because there's a parallel
גמרא Gemara elsewhere that that the question is not are you doing
it now or later but the question is why did it say
you put them in a מגיס Magis you put them in a
bowl? You don't need to use a bowl. You can actually like
when we talked before about cutting up the תמיד Tamid and the
limbs we talked about bringing the limbs directly right, not not in
some vessel. So here you could just take the אימורין Imurin in
your hands and put them on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. You don't actually
need a bowl. And the basic הלכה Halacha is so anyway there
the question is is that what the גמרא's Gemara asking? You know
the גמרא Gemara elsewhere sort of asks that question. The basic הלכה
Halacha is that it's true you don't need a bowl. By a
מנחה Mincha when you take the קומץ Kometz you have to put
it in a vessel because that's part of the sanctification. Here you
don't need it. Of course here you're gonna be waiting you know
an hour. You're not doing it right now. So what are you
already gonna do with them? Right now you might need a bowl.
What are you gonna do put them on the floor? So fine
you put them in a bowl as until you need them. It
is true that when you actually come to put them on the
fire you don't need like the blood like you throw it by
holding the bowl. This is what that's what you do with the
blood. You can actually take them out and use your hand and
put them on the fire but the bowl is just something you
need for the interim because you're not going to be doing it
right now.
Could you put them on the מקום שבית הדשן?
Makom Shebeit HaDeshen? I suppose you could do that.
Anyway they are a pretty heavy quantity of material from an ox.
Yeah the so maybe multiple trips? I don't know.
A big bowl. I don't know. Okay. So anyway but you're not
doing it right now. You're going to later offer them up on
the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. קלען במקלעות. Kila'an Bemakla'ot.
You sort of braided them you know and put them on a
frame to carry them out. אמר רבי יוחנן כמין קליעה Amar Rabbi
Yochanan Kemin Klia like a braid. Okay maybe so they just that
they wouldn't slip you know if they're sort of intertwined they more
give them more surface area or whatever you know lets them one
thing doesn't slip through the holes, it's hold onto the other, the
other animals or the cow and the goat. Fine כמין קליעה. Kemin
Klia. We taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: לא היו מנתחין ניתוח בשר
בשר עולה. Lo hayu m'natchin nituach basar basar olah.
They would not dismember it like they would the meat of an
עולה. olah. אלא, Ella, meaning what? What's the contrast? עור על גבי
בשר. Or al gabei basar. By an עולה olah they would flay
the skin, the leather, and that would be given to the כהנים.
Kohanim. That would obviously be very valuable, the leather of the cow
or whatever or whatever the animal was. Here they would burn it
with the leather, they would not flay it, and they would dismember
it with the leather, the skin on the on the flesh. מנלן
דהא? Minalan de-ha? Where do you know this one? דתניא ותנא ברייתא,
Detanya utan b'raita, רבי אומר: Rebbe omer: נאמר כאן עור בשר ופרש.
Ne'emar kan or basar u-peresh. It says here by the by the
ox and the goat of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it says you
burn them with their flesh, with their skin, their flesh, and their
dung, you know, their excrement. ונאמר להלן, V'ne'emar l'hallan, and it says
over there. It's funny, להלן l'hallan usually means later, but it really
means elsewhere because it's actually earlier in ויקרא. Vayikra. It says by
the two major things that we've talked about in the past that
also the blood goes in the inside of the קרבנות korbanot that
are brought for a communal sin, either פר העלם דבר, Par He'elam
Davar, בית דין Beit Din rules and people sin and you bring
this special ox, or a similar scenario except everybody has sinned with
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. That's פר ושעיר הנעשה בפנים. Par v'se'ir hana'aseh
bifnim. So here's another example actually interestingly an ox and a goat
paralleling this ox and a goat. But anyway those are those are
other קרבנות korbanot that are in the end of פרשת ויקרא, parshat
Vayikra, ויקרא ד, Vayikra dalet, that where it says you bring the
blood on the inside and you take their and you take the
meat and the bodies and whatever and you take it out of
the camp and you burn. Same type of idea. Okay, so here
it says you take them, the skin and the flesh and
the
dung. ונאמר להלן, V'ne'emar l'hallan, it says
later, עור ובשר ופרש. Or u-basar u-peresh. רש"י Rashi quotes the
פסוק: pasuk: it
says
ואת עור הפר ואת כל בשרו על ראשו ועל כרעיו וקרבו ופרשו.
V'et or ha-par v'et kol besaro al rosho v'al k'ra'av v'kirbo u-pirsho.
Okay, the whole
thing, the
flesh and
the
meat, the head, the
legs. על כרעיו וקרבו ופרשו וקרבו, al k'ravav v'kirbo u'firsho v'kirbo, okay,
ופרשו והוציא u'firsho v'hotzi and
you take
it out of
the camp and
you burn it. Okay,
so so
so
what we're
saying is
first of all this על ראשו ועל כרעיו al rosho v'al k'ravav
parallels a פסוק pasuk by
the
עולה. olah. By the עולה olah what
does the תורה Torah say? The basic standard עולה olah at the
beginning of ויקרא. Vayikra. The first case of ויקרא Vayikra
is the עולה olah and it says
והפשיט את העולה ונתח אותה לנתחיה. v'hifshit es ha'olah v'nitach osah l'nesacheha.
Okay so that's
והפשיט v'hifshit by an עולה. olah. והפשיט את העולה ונתח.
v'hifshit es ha'olah
v'nitach. Okay that's cutting it up into, flaying it and cutting it
up. And then it says what do you
do?
וקרבו וכרעיו ירחץ במים.
v'kirbo u'chra'av
yirchatz bamayim. וקרבו וכרעיו. v'kirbo u'chra'av. Okay it's inner and its legs.
So now what we are saying is the following. Because we've got
right ראשו ועל כרעיו? rosho v'al k'ravav?
Do we have ראשו rosho here?
Well we have וקרבו וכרעיו. v'kirbo u'chra'av. Okay. ראשו כרעיו. rosho chra'av.
Where's ראשו? rosho? רש"י Rashi quotes it. Hold on. וערכו בני אהרן
הכהנים את הנתחים את הראש ואת הפדר. v'archu b'nei
aharon hakoanim es han'tachim
es harosh v'es hapader. Okay so later. וערכו בני אהרן את הנתחים
את הראש ואת הפדר. v'archu b'nei aharon es han'tachim es harosh v'es
hapader. And then it says וקרבו וכרעיו. v'kirbo u'chra'av. So they're not
exactly right next to each other. את הראש es harosh וקרבו וכרעיו.
v'kirbo u'chra'av. So here's what we say. Because you have ראש rosho
and כרעיו k'ravav here and because you have ראש rosho and כרעיו
k'ravav there you learn something from an עולה. olah. What do you
learn from an עולה? olah? You learn ונתח. v'nitach. You learn that
you are going to dismember this thing that you bring outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That's what we are going to learn from
the עולה. olah. What are we not going to learn? We're not
going to learn והפשיט. v'hifshit. We are not going to flay this.
We're gonna flay that, that we are not going to flay. We'll
dismember it but we won't flay it. Why not? Because we're basically
saying וקרבו ופרשו והוציא. v'kirbo u'firsho v'hotzi. The same way you are
keeping the פרש, peresh, the undigested matter, בקרבו b'kirbo inside of it
so and you're taking this out as one unit, you're not separating
it, you similarly are not going to separate the עור or and
the בשר. basar. You're going to keep that as one unit as
well. Okay so we learn from an עולה olah that you dismember
it. What we don't learn, what we say though is you do
not flay it because the same way this is understood to mean
they remain together, we understand that the flesh and the meat remain
together as well.
רש"י Rashi says about this עולה olah ורחץ במים. v'rachatz bamayim. Right,
that means that you are separating the פרש. peresh. No,
no
you're not.
Is that what they're doing when they wash?
Well you would be, yes actually that would be true, you would
be doing that.
But that's what they need at the עולה olah to wash all
the stuff out?
Well maybe, but you're putting it in the bowls for later. Anyway,
this is the stuff you bring outside. Let's not confuse what you
bring outside and you burn outside. He took out the innerds that
he's going to burn on the מזבח. mizbeach. But this is the
stuff that's being burnt outside of
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay so that's what we have. We
have that you take the whole thing, the empty carcasses, the deboweled
carcasses, you take them outside. You're going to dismember them, that we
learn from an עולה, olah, but you're not going to flay them.
By the way, as I said, the עולה olah you flay it,
the כהנים kohanim get the skin. Here it's all being burnt anyway
so you do not flay it, you keep the skin on the
meat and you
burn it. ממתי מטמאין בגדים? Meimasai mitamin b'gadim?
Okay so now we get to the stage when in the burning
is the person going to become טמא? tamei? Let's take a look.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught, והוציא אל מחוץ למחנה ושרפו. v'hotzi
el michutz lamachaneh v'sharafu. Okay, this is you shall take them outside
the camp and burn them. This is by the case by יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, by exactly our case. Okay and להלן אתה נותן
להם שלש מחנות וכאן אתה נותן להם מחנה אחת. l'halan atah nosein
lahem shalosh machanos v'kan atah nosein lahem מחנה אחת machaneh achas. So
over there meaning again by the classic case of the by other
cows and goats that are burnt outside, not on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, the case in ויקרא ד Vayikra daled that we've been talking
about, like the כהן גדול Kohen Gradol and so on or a
פר העלם דבר, par helam davar, we're going to learn out that
you burn them. The first thing we're going to be focusing on
here is not when the person becomes טמא tamei but where do
you burn it? When it says והוציא אל מחוץ למחנה, v'hotzi el
michutz lamachaneh, if you remember חז"ל Chazal understand that there are three
camps. There's the מחנה שכינה machaneh shechinah which is where the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash was and in the תורה Torah time it's the
משכן. mishkan. Then there's the מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah, in the תורה
Torah time that is the לויים, Levi'im, in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash time that is הר הבית. Har Habayis. And then there's מחנה
ישראל machaneh Yisrael which is where all the other tribes were and
in the מקדש Mikdash time. ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So when it says take
it out of the מחנה, Machaneh, we're not focusing now on טומאה,
tumah, just where did you burn it. Take it out of the
מחנה Machaneh and burn it, does it mean out of the first
מחנה Machaneh it's in, take it out of מחנה שכינה? Machaneh Shechinah?
Maybe you burn it on הר הבית, Har HaBayit, just take it
out of the מקדש? Mikdash? Or does it mean take it out
of all three מחנות, machanot, take it out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? That's
the question. And the basic point is going to be that we're
going to take for granted that things that are burnt outside, like
פר העלם דבר par helam davar and so on, when they, you
know in ויקרא ד, Vayikra dalet, those things are burnt outside of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Here it's not clear and here we're going to say
we learn from there that this also is burnt outside of all
three camps, outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So let's take a look. יוציא
אל מחוץ למחנה ושרפו. Yotzi el michutz lamachaneh vesarfu. So here by
יום כיפור Yom Kippur take it out of the camp and burn.
להלן את נוהג להם שלש מחנות. Lehalan at noheg lahem shalosh machanot.
Over there by let's say פר העלם דבר, par helam davar, other
cases of things burnt outside, it's outside of all three camps, outside
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. וכאן אתה נותן להם מחנה אחת. Vekahn atah noten
lahem machaneh achat. Here it only says יוציא אל מחוץ למחנה, Yotzi
el michutz lamachaneh, one camp. So here basically you take it right
just outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So is that true?
You burn it on הר הבית? Har HaBayit? So אם כן למה
נאמר מחוץ למחנה? Im kein lamah ne'emar michutz lamachaneh? So,
so if so meaning if it's true that it's not the same
that here too we're going to learn that you need three camps,
that you burn it outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, why is the תורה
Torah making it sound like just take it out of the first
camp, just take it out of the
מקדש? Mikdash? ולמה נאמר מחוץ למחנה? לומר לך כיון שיצא חוץ למחנה
אחת מטמאים בגדים. Velamah ne'emar michutz lamachaneh? Lomar lach kivan sheyatza chutz
lemachaneh achat mitam'im begadim. So not to tell you that you need
to take it out, that you burn it on הר הבית, Har
HaBayit, but to tell you as soon as you took it out
of the first camp, as soon as you took it out of
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that's when the clothes become טמא, tamei,
that's when the person involved with it becomes טמא, tamei, okay? So
is it, is that clear what we're doing? By the normal case
of
right here by
the
פר ושעיר par ve'sa'ir of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur it says
והוציא
אל
מחוץ למחנה,
Vehotzi el michutz
lamachaneh, ושרפו, vesarfu, and then it says what? והשרף אותם יכבס
בגדיו.
Vehasoreif otam
yechabeis begadav. Okay?
So it says אל מחוץ למחנה, el michutz lamachaneh, so one camp.
So that would mean outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The first camp is,
not outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim, excuse me. There's בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is
camp number one, then it's הר הבית Har HaBayit is camp number
two, okay? And then it's ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
when it says take outside of the camp, so that means camp
number one. Go outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, burn it on
הר הבית, Har HaBayit, because it only says one camp. There's nothing
to indicate more. All right. Anyway, but what we're going to find
out is that other things like פר כהן גדול par Kohen Gadol
and the פר העלם דבר, par helam davar, other cases that are
in, that speak about things that are brought, the blood is brought
inside in ויקרא ד, Vayikra dalet, we're going to say that from
there you learn it's three camps, that it's burnt, it's burnt outside
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, burn it outside ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So the question is
if we're going to learn from there that you burn this outside
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, why does it say one camp? To tell you
as soon as you leave the first camp, that's when you become
טמא, tamei, okay?
But then it should say you become טמא tamei when you leave
a camp.
What, I don't, I don't know. Okay. So that's what we learn
out. Let's take a look. Okay. והסא
מנלן, Vehasa minalan, how do you know that by those other cases
it's burnt outside of all three camps, it's burnt outside of ירושלים?
Yerushalayim? דתניא, Detanya, we learn in the ברייתא, baraita, והוציא את כל
הפר, Vehotzi et kol hapar, again that's over there by the פר
כהן גדול. par Kohen Gadol. So you take the whole, the whole
ox. חוץ לשלש מחנות, Chutz leshalosh machanot, outside of all three camps.
אתה אומר חוץ לשלש מחנות, Atah omer chutz leshalosh machanot, you're telling
me outside all three, outside ירושלים? Yerushalayim? או אינו אלא חוץ למחנה
אחת, O eino ela chutz lemachaneh achat, maybe it only means outside
of הר הבית Har HaBayit and you burn outside of the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you burn it on הר הבית? Har HaBayit? כשהוא
אומר Keshehu omer בפר העדה b'far ha'eidah אל מחוץ למחנה, el michutz
lamachaneh, when it says that you burn it אל מחוץ למחנה
el michutz lamachaneh by the, by the I think that's פר העלם
דבר, par helam davar, שאין תלמוד לומר, she'ein talmud lomar, which there's
no need to say, שהרי כבר נאמר ושרף אותו כאשר שרף את
הפר הראשון חטאת הקהל הוא. sheharei kvar ne'emar vesaraf oto ka'asher saraf
et hapar harishon chatat hakahal hu.
So by both by the case of the פר של כהן גדול
par shel Kohen Gadol who sins and by the case of a
פר העלם דבר, par helam davar, it says burn it outside of
the camp. But by the case of the פר העלם דבר par
helam davar it says just like you did the one of the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So if you're already telling me just like
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, why do you have to again repeat
out of the camp? ומה תלמוד לומר מחוץ למחנה? Umah talmud lomar
michutz lamachaneh? ליתן לו מחנה שניה, Leiten lo machaneh shniyah, that gives
you two camps. וכשהוא אומר Ukeshehu omer מחוץ למחנה בדשן, michutz lamachaneh
badeshen,
so basically what do we have? It says by the פר כהן
גדול par Kohen Gadol it says right, מחוץ למחנה. michutz lamachaneh. burned
it outside the camp. By the פר העלם דבר Par He'elem Davar
it says מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh
but it also says כאשר עשה, ka'asher asah, right?
What's the whole פסוק pasuk by this thing?
והוציא את כל הפר אל מחוץ למחנה אל מקום טהור אל שפך
הדשן ושרף אתו על העצים באש על שפך הדשן
ישרף.
v'hotzi et
kol
hapar el michutz lamachaneh el mekom tahor el shefech hadeshen v'saraf oto
al ha'etzim ba'esh al shefech hadeshen yisareif. Right. כאשר עשה את הפר
הראשון. ka'asher asah et hapar harishon. So basically, if you're already telling
me treat them the same, כאשר עשה, ka'asher asah, why do you
repeat מחוץ למחנה? michutz lamachaneh? To tell me get even further out
of the camp. So we have one camp, two camps, and now
we're going to get three camps. Because as Michael just told us,
where does it say you burn it? It says מחוץ למחנה, michutz
lamachaneh, it says אל שפך הדשן, el shefech hadeshen, where you pour
the, where you pour the ashes. And now, where you pour the
ashes? So let's keep on reading. Okay. וכשהוא אומר uch'shehu omer מחוץ
למחנה michutz lamachaneh בדשן b'deshen
when it tells you by the ashes that you pour the ashes
outside of the camp, שאין תלמוד לומר, she'ein talmud lomar, you don't
have to tell me pour the ashes out of the camp, שהרי
כבר נאמר she'harei kvar ne'emar אל שפך הדשן. el shefech hadeshen. It
says you burn these where the ashes are poured, I can infer
that you pour the ashes outside of the camp. So why when
the תורה Torah talks about the תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, taking the
ashes off of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, does it say spill them outside
the camp? Obviously outside the camp! I learn from these other cases
that the ashes are spilled out of the camp. So why does
it say again outside of the camp? תן לו מחנה שלישית tein
lo machaneh shlishit to tell me three camps. Okay? So this is
extra because it says do by this what you did with that,
and by the דשן deshen when it says אל מחוץ למחנה, el
michutz lamachaneh, למחנה lamachaneh
by the דשן, deshen, by the תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, that's extra
because I already know here that the ashes are out of the
camp. So that's telling me a third חוץ למחנה, chutz lamachaneh, so
you burn it outside of all three camps, outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Okay, that was fun.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: That's how you
know normally outside of three camps, but it says one by our
case to tell you that even though you burn it out of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, as soon as you leave the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
is when you become
טמא. tamei. ורבי שמעון v'Rebbe Shimon האי מחוץ למחנה מאי עביד ליה?
hai michutz lamachaneh mai avid leh? ורבי שמעון v'Rebbe Shimon who says
that you only become טמא tamei when you actually burn it, how
does he explain why it says when you leave the camp, which
we're understanding to mean here that when you leave the first camp
you already become טמא? tamei? So what does he do with why
the תורה Torah says when you leave the camp? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא
miba'ei lei lekhid'tanya to teach what we taught in a ברייתא. braitah.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbe Eliezer omer, a teaching of רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer that he would agree with. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says, נאמר
כאן מחוץ למחנה ונאמר להלן מחוץ למחנה. ne'emar kan michutz lamachaneh v'ne'emar
lehallan michutz lamachaneh. Here it says outside of the camp and over
there in במדבר Bamidbar it says מחוץ למחנה. michutz lamachaneh. What's the
case over there? That's the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. מה כאן חוץ
לשלוש מחנות אף להלן חוץ לג' מחנות. ma kan chutz l'shalosh machanot
af lehallan chutz l'gimmel machanot. Where do you do the עבודה avodah
of the פרה אדומה? parah adumah? How far out? Maybe you could
do it just out of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, maybe you
do it in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? No! The same way we know that
all of this stuff is outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, outside of three
camps, the extra מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh here is going to teach
me to link to a similar word by the פרה אדומה parah
adumah that the פרה אדומה parah adumah is outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim
as well.
What was it outside ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
No, the פרה אדומה parah adumah they did it on הר הזיתים
Har HaZeitim on the east.
But here I mean...
Oh here I don't know where it was.
No מזבח? mizbe'ach?
No, no, no, you didn't do an act of הקרבה, hakaravah, you
just burned it.
Right, right, yeah, that's outside
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, הר הזיתים Har HaZeitim is outside of ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
Yeah, that's a good point, right, it's not just outside of הר
הבית, Har HaBayit, it's outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I guess the ancient
ירושלים Yerushalayim would be, it's true, it's true. Okay, yes, so they
get the linkage to outside of the three מחנות machanot because it
says מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh or
is that just רבי שמעון? Rebbe Shimon? Because how do the חכמים
Chachamim know to connect it?
We don't know that.
The חכמים Chachamim have not connected it to פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
Okay, but yeah, that's a good point, I wasn't even stopping to
think of it nowadays, it wouldn't occur to us that הר הזיתים
Har HaZeitim is out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
but you know, the ancient ירושלים, Yerushalayim, when you go on those
tours you see like the עיר דוד Ir David or whatever, it's
tiny, you know. ומה להלן במזרחה של ירושלים, u'mah lehallan bemizrachah shel
Yerushalayim, now we say something else that we learn it in the
reverse, okay, that the same way the פרה אדומה parah adumah it's
done on the east of ירושלים Yerushalayim at הר הזיתים Har HaZeitim
because it says you have to sprinkle the blood towards the opening
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so you have to be east of הר
הבית Har HaBayit in order to be looking at the opening of
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, אף כאן במזרחה של ירושלים. af kan bemizrachah shel
Yerushalayim.
He says where you did this burning of the carcasses and the
ashes would be on the east. So he uses this extra word
to link it to the פרה אדומה parah adumah to learn both
ways. פרה אדומה parah adumah is out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but this
is also to the east of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ורבנן, v'rabbanan, היכי שרפי
ליה? heichi sharfi lei?
And the rabbis, the גמרא Gemara is not bothered with Michael's question,
which I also was wondering, where do the rabbis know you do
the פרה אדומה parah adumah out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Presumably that we
get somewhere else. Okay, but How about the other point, where do
they say you did the burning here? So where did you burn
it? Would they agree it's to the east? No. כדתניא Kiditanya like
we saw in the ברייתא, Braisa, היכא נשרפין heicha nisrafin where would
they be burnt? לצפונה של ירושלים, Litzfonah shel Yerushalayim, the north of
ירושלים Yerushalayim בחוץ לשלוש מחנות. bechutz leshalosh machanos. Why the north? So
as רש"י Rashi says, שכל חטאת בצפון, shekol chatas batzafon,
normally if you have any question where you do something and you're
dealing with a sin offering, you do it in the north. It's
slaughtered on the north of the מזבח. mizbeiach. North is the direction
for a חטאת. chatas. So they say you would do it to
the north of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So again, what do we say? We're
saying that from all these cases of the פר במקרא ד', par
b'Vayikra daled, פר כהן גדול, Par Kohen Gadol, פר העלם דבר, Par
He'elam Davar,
we know it's burnt out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Therefore here we know
it's burnt out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Why does it say מחוץ למחנה
michutz lamachaneh which suggests seems to be extra if we can have
this linkage? Either to tell me you become טמא tamei as soon
as you leave the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or out of one
מחנה, machaneh, or according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to link it
to the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah to tell me the פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah is outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim to tell me that this
like the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is to the east of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. וחכמים Vachachamim don't use it for that. They tell me
you become טמא tamei when you leave the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
They say you would burn it not to the east but to
the north of ירושלים Yerushalayim because the basic direction of a חטאת
chatas is to the north. So for the חכמים Chachamim you would
burn it here, here you would do the שריפה sreifah out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim to the north, and according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon you would do it here, out of ירושלים Yerushalayim
to the east.
Okay, let's do
a little bit more outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
What? Everybody reads that ברייתא. Braisa. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer
על בית הדשן נשרפין. al beis hadeshen nisrafin. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says that it would be burnt on the בית הדשן. beis hadeshen.
Now what's the חידוש? chiddush? We already said you know this is
the place שפך הדשן shepach hadeshen etc. So of course we know
this is where you burn it, where you do all the other
ashes where you pour the ashes of the תרומת הדשן, Trumas Hadeshen,
where you would burn other קרבנות korbanos that had the blood brought
on the inside of the היכל. Heichal. So the חידוש chiddush seems
to be is assumed to be that he's saying there has to
be ashes there. You can't burn it unless there's already ashes there,
okay? Because since the תורה Torah says שפך הדשן shepach hadeshen it
means not just the place where the ashes are, there literally has
to be ashes. אמר רבא Amar Rava meaning if
they blew away it wouldn't be good?
No, meaning not the ashes from this, from that, from the מזבח
mizbeiach for the תרומת הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen. Correct. אמר רבא מאן תנא
דפליג עליה דרבי יוסי Amar Rava man tanna d'palig alei d'Rabbi Yossi
it's a good question what would we do?
It might be closed. It might be in an enclosed area.
Burning it, I don't know, all these carcasses, you do not want
to be burning all these carcasses in an enclosed area.
I might be just for the דשן deshen I mean, so it
wouldn't be.
Yeah, maybe they just put a tarp over it. Okay. אמר רבא
מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי יוסי Amar Rava man tanna d'palig alei
d'Rabbi Yossi who disagrees with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and says there
does not have to be ashes literally ashes where you burn it?
It's the place you pour the ashes, but it doesn't literally have
to be ashes. So רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov.
דתניא Ditanya it says in a ברייתא Braisa על שפך הדשן ישרף
al shepach hadeshen yisareif שיהא שם דשן sheyehai sham deshen there has
to be ashes there. That's pretty clear. By the way, that's not
a פסוק pasuk by our case of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's
a פסוק pasuk by what do you call it? By the other
cases, by ויקרא ד', Vayikra daled, by like the פר העלם דבר.
Par He'elam Davar. But presumably we're learning them all out from one
another. So since it's described at שפך הדשן shepach hadeshen it means
literally there has to be ashes. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov omer שיהא מקומו משופך sheyehai mekomo meshupach it doesn't
mean ashes has to be there, it means it has to be
a sloped, so that were you to pour ashes they would sort
of spill down. It has to be a sloped place even if
there aren't literally ashes there. So that's the debate. אמר אביי Amar
Abaye אביי Abaye says דילמא במקום משופך הוא דפליגי? dilma b'makom meshupach
hu d'paligi? How do you know that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is
denying the need for ashes? Maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is adding
an extra criterion. You חכמים Chachamim say it's enough to be ashes,
I say שפך shepach requires more than just ashes. דשן deshen requires
ashes, שפך shepach requires that it be a sloped place that where
you pour the ashes it slopes, but maybe he agrees that you
require ashes. Okay, so now we know you do it outside of
ירושלים Yerushalayim to the north according to חכמים Chachamim to the east
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and we are saying that it
says it says here that you pour it על שפך הדשן. al
shepach hadeshen. Did I not write that? Anyway you pour yeah על
שפך הדשן al shepach hadeshen you pour it where the ashes of
the תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen are. So now we are saying does
that literally mean there have to be ashes, or is it just
the place where those ashes are normally put? What about? And she's
actually pouring it
as opposed to placing it down?
I know, so but it's not telling you it's the תרומת הדשן,
Trumas Hadeshen, it's telling you where you do these פרים parim or
whatever these things אל שפך הדשן. el shepach hadeshen. תנו רבנן Tanu
Rabbanan now we get to the idea of becoming טמא. tamei. The
one who burns it becomes טמא. tamei. We've just said according to
the חכמים Chachamim as soon as you leave as soon as you
leave the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash as opposed to שמעון Shimon who
says when you're actually burning it, so let's take a look who
becomes טמא. tamei. דתנו רבנן והשרף אותם יכבס בגדיו Detanu Rabbanan Vehasoreif
osam yichabeis begadav the one who burns them, הסורף מטמא בגדים hasoreif
metamei vegadim
only the one who burns them ולא המצית את האור velo hamatzis
es ha'or not the guy who lights the fire, okay? So So
this obviously we're going within the idea of רב שמעון Reb Shimon
that you only become טמא tamei when you actually burn them because
otherwise we'd be talking about who's taking it out of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay. We're talking that you actually when you actually
burn it, and here saying you have to be the one who
burns, not the one who does the preparatory stuff, not the one
who gets the fire going, ולא המסדר את המערכה, velo hamasader es
hamarachah, not the one who, you know, builds up the fire pyre,
the wood. So only the guy that actually burns
it. ואיזהו הסורף, Ve'eizehu hasoreif, who is the, how do you identify
the one who burns it? זה המסייע בשעת שריפה. Zeh hamisayeya b'shas
sreifah. It's not, anybody who participates during the time of burning. So
not at the preparatory times. So that raises an interesting question, what
does participate mean? So we put the animal, the carcass on the
wood pile, okay. If you're moving around the carcass and turning it
over so that it burns, you're obviously סורף. soreif. Let's say the
carcass is on the wood pile and you're adding a log of
wood, right? That's also מסייע בשעת שריפה. misayeya b'shas sreifah. So it
sounds like anybody who does any part of that burning, whether you're
dealing with the animal or dealing with the wood pile during the
time that it's burning, then you're סורף, soreif, then you become טמא.
tamei. Okay. יכול אף משנעשו אפר, Yachol af mishe'nasu eifer, maybe even
when it becomes ashes, if you keep on burning it even after
it's ashes you become מטמא בגדים? metamei begadim? תלמוד לומר אותם, Talmud
lomar osam, the one who burns them, when they still have their
identity as a carcass. אותם מטמא בגדים, Osam metamei begadim, only when
you, you know, they're a carcass and you're burning them then you
become טמא, tamei, ולא משנעשו אפר מטמא בגדים. velo mishe'nasu eifer metamei
begadim. If you continue to burn it once it's already ashes, then
it's already doesn't exist anymore and you don't become טמא. tamei. ורבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר, Verabbi Eliezer b'Rebbi Shimon omer, הפר מטמא, hapar
metamei, only the, it says הפר hapar when it's an ox it
becomes makes you טמא. tamei. ניתך הבשר, Nizach habasar, once the flesh
has already become dissolved, אינו מטמא בגדים, eino metamei begadim, it's not.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? It sounds like
they're saying the same thing, once it's ashes, it doesn't make you
טמא. tamei. What's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says איכא בינייהו
דשוייה חרוכה. ika beinaihu d'shavei charuchah. No, the difference is when it's
charcoal but not ashes, right? You could have a piece of meat
that's totally charred and totally black, but it's not yet ashes. So
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says as soon as
the meat is basically destroyed you don't become טמא, tamei, so even
before ashes. Whereas the חכמים Chachamim say no, it has to actually
become ashes in order for it to no longer be considered the
carcass, to
identify this as
a burnt piece of flesh, but it's still flesh, only when it
becomes ashes is it something different. Okay, so here it's if you
say you become טמא tamei when you actually burn it, not just
when you leave ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what is defined as burning it? A,
it can't be ashes, B, you have to be directly involved with
the fire and with the burning it when it's on the fire,
not in doing preparatory things. By the way, although רש"י Rashi says
this is going according to רב שמעון, Reb Shimon, it could be
going according to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Even though the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says you become טמא tamei when you leave ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, let's say one guy took it out when you leave the
הר הבית, Har Habayis, when you leave the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
let's say one guy took it out of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, he brought it to this place, and then other people were
involved in burning it. Would the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say that
if they literally are the ones that are burning it they don't
become טמא? tamei? The Torah says the one who burns it becomes
טמא. tamei. So presumably the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma doesn't deny that
that's a time when you can become טמא, tamei, he just says
that you also become טמא tamei the minute you leave the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, so I don't know why רש"י Rashi says
it's only going according to רב שמעון. Reb Shimon. תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says the טומאה tumah begins earlier, but presumably anybody involved in
the burning of it also becomes טמא. tamei.
Yeah, it's interesting, like almost like on יום כיפור Yom Kippur it's
מותר, mutar, because you could have said let them set up the
fire before יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, put on a lot of logs,
be a nice raging fire, so no one's going to have
to make a fire on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Yeah, so that
gets to the whole הותרה דחויה hutrah dechuyah question, where we tend
to totally say הותרה hutrah if it's a קרבן korban that's done
today, you know, זמנו zmano is today. So right, the גמרא Gemara
does not discuss, by the way, this is talking not about the
יום כיפור Yom Kippur case, it's talking about like the פר העלם
דבר, par helam davar, so we're talking about a regular day. I
understand, but we don't know, maybe they didn't really tend to the
fire, maybe they just threw it on, I don't know. Okay, so
now we move on. So now he's got this stuff, he's got
the אימורים, emurim, that he's going, we learn that he's going to
burn the אימורים emurim later, the carcasses are being sent out of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash through somebody else, they're going to be
burnt outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and now we sort of get a
moment of closure in terms of what else has been going on,
which is the goat has been going, the other goat, remember he
sent a little while ago to go over the cliff. So אמרו
לו לכהן גדול, amru lo l'Kohen Gadol, they said to the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, הגיע שעיר למדבר, higia sa'ir l'midbar, the goat has
come to the desert, to the wilderness. ומנין היו יודעים, Uminayin hayu
yodim, until that has happened, you look at רש"י, Rashi, the משנה,
Mishnah, אמרו לכהן גדול שאינו רשאי להתחיל בעבודה אחרת עד שיגיע שעיר
למדבר. amru l'Kohen Gadol she'eino rasha'i lehatchil b'avodah acheres ad she'yagia sa'ir
l'midbar. He can't begin the next stage, meaning he can finish up
the goat and the ox and get their carcasses sent outside, but
you can't go ahead and do something new from the goat and
the oxes and that whole process until the goat gets to the
wilderness. Why not? Well we'll see in a minute. Okay, that's reading
the Torah. That's the next thing. How do we know that? שנאמר
ושילח את השעיר המדבר ואחר כך ואת חלב החטאת יקטיר המזבחה. shene'emar
ve-shilach es ha-sa'ir ha-midbar ve-achar kach ve-es chelev ha-chatat yaktir ha-mizbeicha. So
even though the immediate next thing he does is not the burning
of the fats, nevertheless, there's a sense you have to wait for
that moment to happen before you move on. So right now he
did not really do anything else of significance, right? Cutting open their
carcasses and taking out the inners is not yet an עבודה. avodah.
And then he got them sent to go outside, okay, but he's
not going to do anything else now until we get done with
what we're in the middle of, we get done with this aspect
of the שעיר sa'ir and he finds out that it got to
the wilderness. ומנין היו יודעים שהגיע שעיר למדבר? u-minayin hayu yode'im she-higia
sa'ir la-midbar? How would he know when that moment occurred? דורכאות היו
עושים, dirka'ot hayu osim, they would make דורכאות dirka'ot which would be
like, רש"י Rashi says it means like appointed people that would be
standing there and they'd do a whole flag waving. It's obviously some
Greek word. Does anybody have the Steinzaltz? He'll tell you what the
Greek word is. No, Charlie would... What? Yeah, you can catch your
breath for a moment while you're waiting. Is it Brachia? Or boost
of the Mincha or something? Maybe, exactly. Let's see. How did they
translate? Oh, platforms is what he says. That's interesting. According to most
versions of the text, the term here should be דידקיות, didkiyot, not
דורכאות. dirka'ot. The origin of the word is the Greek didokas meaning
a rearguard or messengers who bring news from an army's front lines.
That's how רש"י Rashi reads it. רש"י Rashi reads it more as
messengers. Okay, but he says maybe it also means could mean platforms.
Right, so you could see the flag waving, exactly. ומניפין בסודרין, u-menifin
bi-sudarin, so you know, they would have people at different locations. Maybe
it would be the same people at in the סוכות, sukkot, I
don't know, who would then and they'd wave with
the flags when the goat would get, and you know, it would
be like a daisy chain.
One guy would wave and then the next guy would see and
then he would wave.
Sort of like they sent the
message of when they did the קידוש החודש Kiddush ha-Chodesh with the
fires. Except though you don't do fires, it's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
so you know, everybody sees the guy right before him down the
lane and the word gets communicated all the way back to the
בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash. They would wave the flag ויודעים שהגיע שעיר
למדבר ve-yod'im she-higia sa'ir la-midbar and they knew it got to the
wilderness. אמר רבי יהודה והלא סימן גדול היה להם. Amar Rabbi Yehuda
ve-halo siman gadol haya la-hem. No, they have an even easier way
of just telling the time. מירושלים ועד בית חידודו. Miyerushalayim ve-ad Beis
Chidudo. From Yerushalayim until the place where it is, of its sharpness,
of its like which basically רש"י Rashi says but you would think
that means the cliff. But remember it got to the wilderness way
before it went over the cliff. Okay, so somehow this word בית
חידודו Beis Chidudo means means the place where the wilderness begins. If
you look at the side, the ירושלמי'ס Yerushalmi's גרסא girsa is בית
חורון, Beis Choron, right, which is a place outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Where is בית חורון Beis Choron located? Does anybody know? North, east,
south, west? Go to Google Maps or something. Anyway, so so that
would be interesting because that would tell you the direction in which
they're taking the goat if we knew where בית חורון Beis Choron
was. Anyway, that would be considered the edge of the wilderness. שלושה
מילין, shlosha milin, it takes three מיל mil to get to the
edge of the wilderness. והולכין מיל, ve-holchin mil, so the guys that
would accompany it out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right, the guy with the
goat, they'd go a מיל, mil, 2,000 אמה, amma, about a kilometer.
וחוזרין מיל, ve-chozrin mil, then they'd come back, they'd do their return
journey, that would be two מיל. mil. ושוהים כדי מיל, ve-shohim k'dei
mil, you wait the time it takes to go a מיל, mil,
which you would roughly know. ויודעים שהגיע שעיר למדבר, ve-yod'im she-higia sa'ir
la-midbar, and you would know. So you just estimate. You don't need
direct eyewitness testimony and the waving of the flags. You just give
it the time it takes to go three מיל, mil, three kilometers,
and then it's already considered the beginning of the מדבר. midbar. How
what? Northwest, בית חורון? Beis Choron? Do you have a topographic map?
Is there like mountains in that region that they can throw it
off? Okay. How far is it from ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Okay. According to
this it should be around three kilometers from the הר הבית, Har
ha-Bayis, but... North as מודיעין. Modi'in. North is מודיעין. Modi'in. מודיעין Modi'in
is much more than three kilometers, isn't it? Three kilometers is like
what, two miles? Okay, anyway. Okay, anyway, he says it would be
three מיל, mil, three kilometers, you would estimate it, then you would
know that it got to the מדבר. midbar. Didn't go over the
cliff, but it got to the מדבר. midbar. רבי ישמעאל אומר והלא
סימן אחר היה להם. Rabbi Yishmael omer ve-halo siman acher haya la-hem.
What do you mean? You don't need to guess the time, you
don't need to wave the flags. You got a great סימן. siman.
לשון של זהורית היה קשור על פתחו של היכל. Lashon shel zehoris
haya kashur al pitcho shel heichal. Now we're tying back to this,
right? Remember they would have the red string on the door of
the היכל, heichal, the opening. וכשהגיע שעיר למדבר היה לשון מלבין, u-keshe-higia
sa'ir la-midbar haya lashon malbin, and then it would turn white. שנאמר
אם יהיו חטאיכם כשנים כשלג ילבינו. shene'emar im yihyu chata'eichem kashanim kashaleg
yalbinu. Now of course we learned that in certain times it didn't
turn white when it was, you know, when the people weren't deserving,
if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wasn't deserving. We learned that it
didn't remain by the doorway, they put it on the goat or
they put it behind the doorway. But anyway, he's at least referring
to a time when it did turn white and when it was
on the door. he says then you would know. And again notice,
although it hasn't gone over the cliff, it just got to the
מדבר, midbar, that's the moment when the בגדים bgadim become טמא, tamei,
that's the moment when it's considered נעשית מצותה, na'aseit mitzvatah, the basic
מצוה mitzvah is done, and that's also when the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol can begin the next stage, which is what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, שמע מינה, shma mina, בית חידודי Beis
Chidudi במדבר. bamidbar. We hear that בית חידודי Beis Chidudi means the-
it's in the wilderness or it means the beginning of the wilderness.
Again, he doesn't tell us what the word בית חידודי Beis Chidudi
means.
Again, according to the ירושלמי'ס Yerushalmi's גרסה, girsa, בית חורון, Beis Choron,
it's much more significant.
It's telling us that already begins or presumably after you leave
בית חורון Beis Choron begins the wilderness.
במדבר קיימא, Bamidbar kayma,
it's located in the wilderness. דהא קמשמע לן, Deha kamashma lan, it's
also puzzling me because סבר רבי יהודה, savar Rabbi Yehuda, people take
out רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is,
you know, he might- it's not really debated what we learn from
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
כיון שהגיע למדבר נעשית מצותה,
Keivan she-higia
lamidbar na'aseit
mitzvatah, that although you're supposed to push it off the cliff, and
although as we said, maybe you're יוצא yotzei the עבודה avoda once
you do the וידוי, viduy, okay, בדיעבד, bedi'avad, but to say you
did the מצוה mitzvah of שילוח השעיר shiluach hase'ir and you got
the atonement, that's once it gets to the wilderness even before it
goes over the cliff. הדרן לך שני שעירים. Hadran lach shenei se'irim.
So now we are, phew, the same way the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol could take a moment break waiting for the שעיר se'ir to
get to the מדבר, midbar, take a breath, realize that we just
went through what we see as the focus of the עבודה, avoda,
the whole עבודה avoda that we say in the דאוונינג, davening, from
the taking of the תורה Torah to the, you know, שחיטה shechita
part, you do the scooping of the קטורת, ketoret, you do the
blood, you do the burning of the קטורת, ketoret, excuse me, that's,
you know, the main- you know, the big focus of the bringing
of the קטורת ketoret inside. You do the blood of the פר,
par, you do the blood of the שעיר se'ir inside, on the
פרוכת, parochet, on- you spill it on the base of the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, you- excuse me, you spill out the base, you know, you
do it on the golden מזבח, mizbe'ach, you spill at the base
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You start- you get the carcasses on their
way out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ready to be burned. You have the
innards ready to bring up later. And now the שעיר se'ir has
gotten to the wilderness. Now we take a break, and now we
can get on to the next stage. So we now turn to
the משנה mishna for now the new stage now that all of
that עבודה avoda is done. בא לו כהן גדול לקרות. Ba lo
Kohen Gadol likros. So the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol came now to
read from the תורה. Torah. אם רצה לקרות בבגדי בוץ, Im ratza
likros bivgadei vutz, if he wants to read in his linen garments,
the one he's been doing the עבודה avoda in, בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehuna, קורא, korei, he can. ואם לאו, Ve-im lav, and if he
doesn't want to use those same nice linen garments, קורא באיצטלית לבן
משלו, korei be-itztalit lavan mishelo, he can use his own white tunic.
So he'd change out of the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, go into
his clothes a little bit and then go change back into those
clothes. Exactly. Yep, he would change out- yeah, he could change out.
With all these other קידוש ידים ורגלים? kiddush yadayim v'raglayim? Yeah, well
based on the debate of when you do the קידוש ידים ורגלים,
kiddush yadayim v'raglayim, he would do it. Now חזן הכנסת נוטל ספר
תורה. Chazzan Haknesset notel sefer Torah. Now the חזן Chazzan of the
synagogue- what synagogue? Where- where's this happening? So רש"י Rashi says that
there was a synagogue- רש"י, Rashi, if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
בית הכנסת, Beis Haknesset, about eight lines down from the new- from
the beginning of the new paragraph, he says, האי בית הכנסת היה
סמוך לעזרה בהר הבית. Hai Beis Haknesset haya samuch la'azarah be-Har HaBayit.
Over there on Temple Mount, they had a little שול, shul, pretty
ironic, right? Because we're always told about the שולס shuls as being
a substitute for the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now you've got the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash right there, oh but wait, I've got a
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I've got to catch מנחה. Mincha. All right,
so there's a little שול shul right there on הר הבית Har
HaBayit to catch מנחה Mincha then you go whatever. All right, so
they had a little שול. shul. So shocking though, the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is leaving the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash right there in
the middle of- of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, of the עבודה, avoda,
right? I always imagined that he is- רש"י Rashi says it was
חוץ ל-. chutz le-. No, the חזן הכנסת Chazzan Haknesset is going,
that's where the בית הכנסת Beis Haknesset was. Oh, which כנסת Knesset
are we talking about? But not that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
is actually there. Oh, okay, you could be right, you could be
right. We did have an idea before, if you remember, about somebody
spitting on the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol where it sounded like he
also left the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay. Yeah, there's no place.
Right, right, right, right, right, right. Look, yes, yes, yes, yes, true.
Okay. And by the way, in terms of when does he do
the washing of the hands if he changed his clothes, that's the
next משנה. mishna. All right, anyway, we'll have to discuss where he
did this. Okay. It wasn't של יוחנן, shel Yochanan, was it? It
was for- no, because anyway, so anyway, whatever that local בית הכנסת
Beis Haknesset is, so the חזן Chazzan would- כנסת נוטל ספר תורה,
Knesset notel sefer Torah, would take a ספר תורה sefer Torah ונותנו
לראש הכנסת, ve-nosno l'rosh haknesset, give it to the president. You see,
they had presidents of the שול shul even then, they really did,
we know that by archaeology and inscriptions that they had these presidents,
although רש"י Rashi says the president is what we would call the
גבאי. gabbai. רש"י Rashi says ראש הכנסת על פיו נחתכין צרכי הכנסת,
Rosh Haknesset al piv nechtachin tzarchei haknesset, who's מפטיר, maftir, who פורס
על שמע, pors al shma, who עובר לפני התיבה, over lifnei hateiva,
gives out the honors, okay, um but anyway, but okay, the head
of the synagogue, actually what- there's a Greek term archisynagogos or something
we find on inscriptions, okay, וראש הכנסת נותנו לסגן, ve-rosh haknesset nosno
lasgan, he gives it to the- to the סגן sgan vice- כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, והסגן נותנו לכהן גדול, ve-hasgan nosno l'kohen gadol, so
there's all this whole big... build up and climax of getting the
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, passing it through, going to the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. והכהן גדול עומד ומקבל, vehaKohen Gadol omed umekabel, he receives
it, וקורא אחרי מות ואך
בעשור.
vekorei Acharei Mot
ve'ach be'asor.
He reads the פסוקים psukim of אחרי מות, Acharei Mot, the עבודה
avoda of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and the אך בעשור ach be'asor
which is in אמור, Emor, which is the paragraph of the מוסף.
musaf.
וגלל ספר תורה ומניחו בחיקו, vegalal Sefer Torah uminiho becheiko, he scrolls
it up,
he puts it in his chest, it was small presumably. So he
has it clearly, it's closed, he's not looking at it, he's done.
It's very obvious he's done. ואומר ve'omer and he says יותר ממה
שקראתי לפניכם כתוב כאן. Yosser mi mah shekarasi lifneichem kasuv kan. More
than I have just read is written here. Obviously, it's a big...
there's a lot in the תורה, Torah, but no, he's saying it
because of the next point. ובעשור שבחומש הפקודים uve'asor shebachumash hapikudim and
the other place where the תורה Torah talks about the מוסף, musaf,
which is the פסוק pasuk בעשור לחודש be'asor lachodesh in במדבר, Bamidbar,
in פנחס, Pinchas, right? פנחס Pinchas is the major place where there's
the מוספים. musafim. So then קורא על פה. korei al peh. He
reads that outside, not from the ספר. sefer. So that's why right
there would be טירחא דציבורא, tircha detzibura, it's one thing to go
from one part of ויקרא Vayikra to the next, we'll talk about
it anyway, but to go from the mid ויקרא Vayikra to the
end of במדבר Bamidbar to do the whole rolling, that's טירחא דציבורא,
tircha detzibura, so he just says it out loud, but that's why
he makes it obvious he's closing it and he's reading it בעל
פה. ba'al peh. Don't think, right, that I am, you know, that
this פרשה parsha is written right next to this other פרשה, parsha,
you know? I'm reading this בעל פה. ba'al peh. He makes that
announcement and then he says that last section from פנחס. Pinchas. Okay,
right. Anyway, ואומר, ve'omer, okay, fine. And now ומברך עליה שמונה ברכות.
umevarech aleha shemoneh berachot.
He says eight ברכות berachot after reading the תורה. Torah. What does
he say?
על התורה, Al haTorah, right? אשר נתן לנו תורת אמת, Asher nasan
lanu torat emet, ועל העבודה, ve'al ha'avoda, by the עבודה, avoda, which
basically is a type of a רצה, retzeh, except our עבודה, avoda,
he's just finished the עבודה. avoda. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says it
ends ואותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד, ve'otcha levadcha b'yira na'avod, the way we
end רצה retzeh when we have ברכת כהנים. birchat kohanim. ועל ההודאה,
ve'al hahodaya, giving thanks, מודיים אנחנו לך, modim anachnu lach, okay, which
רש"י Rashi quotes a פסוק pasuk where we learn out that
after the עבודה avoda follows a thanksgiving for God giving us this
opportunity.
Okay, ועל מחילת העוון, ve'al mechilat ha'avon, which is obviously a focus
of the whole עבודה. avoda. ומברך, umevarech, if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, מוחל עונותינו ביום הכפורים מלך מוחל וסולח לעונותינו ולעונות עמו בית
ישראל. mocheil avonotenu b'yom hakippurim melech mocheil vesolayach la'avonotenu vela'avonot amo beit
yisrael. So רש"י Rashi is drawing on our current liturgy and that
is the ברכה beracha of God forgiving us on this יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. ועל המקדש בפני עצמו, ve'al hamikdash bifnei atzmo, that God
should continue to dwell in the מקדש. mikdash.
רש"י Rashi says the חתימה chatima would be ברוך שבחר במקדש. baruch
shebachar bamikdash. ועל הכהנים? ve'al hakohanim? Yes, these are ברוך אתה ה',
Baruch Atah Hashem, and these are just the category, the topic of
the ברכה. beracha. השם מפורש? Hashem meforash? No, presumably not. ועל ישראל
בפני עצמם ve'al yisrael bifnei atzman for ישראל, Yisrael, that God should
be good to them or forgive them, presumably be good because he
already said about the forgiving of sin. ועל ישראל בפני עצמם, ve'al
yisrael bifnei atzman, ועל ירושלים בפני עצמו, ve'al yerushalayim bifnei atzmo, God
should continue, you know, to dwell in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ועל הכהנים בפני
עצמן. ve'al hakohanim bifnei atzman. It's interesting, כהנים kohanim is separated from
ישראל Yisrael by ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Again, that old question of whether כהנים
kohanim are seen as part of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or
not. So here a special ברכה beracha just for the כהנים kohanim
after mentioning... after the ברכה beracha of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. רש"י Rashi says
the ברכה beracha would be שבחר בזרעו של אהרן. shebachar b'zaro shel
aharon. Okay, ועל שאר התפילה, ve'al shear hatefilla, and on the rest
of the prayer, we'll see what that means, בניחותא. binichuta. So we'll
see what that means. הרואה כהן גדול כשהוא קורא אינו רואה פר
ושעיר הנשרפים. Haro'eh Kohen Gadol kshehu korei eino ro'eh par v'sa'ir hanisrafim.
The person who sees the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol being... reading will
not be able to see the burning of the פר ושעיר. par
v'sa'ir. הרואה פר ושעיר הנשרפים אינו רואה כהן גדול כשהוא קורא. Haro'eh
par v'sa'ir hanisrafim eino ro'eh Kohen Gadol kshehu korei. ולא מפני שאינו
רשאי, v'lo mipnei she'eino rashai, it's not like you're not allowed to
witness both, אלא שהיתה דרך רחוקה, ela shehayeta derech rechoka, they were,
right, one was out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, one was right there on
הר הבית, Har Habayit, ומלאכתן שתיהן כאחד, umelachtan sheteihen ke'echad, and they
took place simultaneously. So you can't be in two places at once.
There's a problem about dancing at two weddings. So what I want
to start with talking about tomorrow where we end here is the
question, what was the purpose of this קריאת התורה? krias haTorah? Why
is it assumed that now there is a קריאת התורה? krias haTorah?
We will pick up... that's not in the גמרא, Gemara, but I
wanted to start... we'll pick up with that first thing tomorrow. Especially
if you're reading what he just did as a kind of a
summary of what he did.